All right, let's see how we could implement this function, countBlocks.
好了 我们来看看要如何实现这个函数 countBlocks
It takes this integer levels as input
它的参数是这个 int levels
which is the number of levels the pyramid is made up of,
也就是金字塔的层数
and returns an integer which is equal to the number of blocks it needs.
该函数会返回一个整数 即金字塔所需的方块数量
The first thing we need to do is declare and initialize this total variable here.
首先 我们需要声明并初始化这个变量 total
This will keep track of the number of blocks it needs to build
该变量会随层数一层层叠加而不断变化
the entire pyramid by adding every level one by one.
从而跟踪建造整座金字塔所需的方块数
Then, we start a loop that counts from one to the number of levels in this pyramid,
然后 我们创建一个循环 从 1 一直计数到金字塔的最高层数
and the increment is just i++.
增量就为 i++
Inside the loop and for each level,
在循环里
we need to calculate the number of blocks in that level which is equal to i times i,
我们需要计算每层的方块数 也就是 i 乘以 i
because i changes from one, two,
因为 i 会从 1、2、3
three, all the way until the maximum number of levels.
一直变到金字塔的最高层数为止
Once we calculate that number of what's needed for that level,
我们每算完一层所需的方块数
we just add it to our total variable and update total to be equal to the sum.
就把该值加到变量 total 里 更新 total 变量 使其等于总和
Finally, when the loop ends,
最后 待循环结束
we just return the variable,
我们就返回出变量 total 的值
total, because it would have
因为这就是
the total number of blocks for all the levels in the pyramid.
金字塔每层方块数的总和
Let's test it out for a three-level pyramid,
我们来测试这段代码 假设金字塔是三层的
which means our input variable levels here is going to be three,
也就是说这里的输入变量 levels 为 3
total is initialized to zero,
total 则初始化为 0
and our loop goes from one to levels which happens to be three.
循环会从 1 开始一直执行到 levels 也就是 3
Now let's keep track of every variable we have as we go through the loop.
我们来执行循环并跟踪每个变量
i starts by one,
i 一开始为 1
and then we check this condition if i is less than or equal to levels which is basically,
然后我们判断这个条件 i 是否小于或等于 levels
if i is less than or equal to three,
也就是判断 i 是否小于或等于 3
and that is true because i is still one.
结果为真 因为 i 现在还是 1
So we calculate the number of blocks in
于是我们计算这一层的方块数
that particular level over here which is i times i,
也就是 i 乘以 i
and then we add the result of i times i to total,
然后将 i 乘以 i 的结果与 total 相加
which started as zero so makes total equal to one.
而 total 一开始为 0 于是 total 变为 1
We reached the end of the first loop, so we go back up,
到达第一次循环的尾部 我们回到这上面来
add one to i, making it equal to two,
给 i 加 1 使其为 2
and then check the condition again.
再次进行条件判断
Is i less than or equal to three?
i 是否小于或等于 3？
And it's still two, so that's true.
因为现在 i 还是 2 所以条件为真
So we calculate i times i which is two times two,
于是我们计算 i 乘以 i 也就是 2 乘以 2
happens to be four,
结果为 4
and add that to total.
将 4 与 total 相加
Total was already one,
因为 total 现在为 1
so we add that, making it five.
所以加了之后就是 5 了
We reached the end of this loop again so we go back up,
再次到达循环尾部 我们再回来
we add one to i, making it three.
给 i 加 1 使其为 3
We do this check again,
再次判断
is three less than or equal to three?
3 是否小于或等于 3？
Yes it is, because it is equal to three, so that's true.
对的 因为 3 等于 3 所以条件为真
So we step inside again,
再次进入循环
and calculate i times i, making it nine.
计算 i 乘以 i 得到结果为 9
Just three times three,
因为是 3 乘以 3
add that to total which was five.
将其与 total 相加 而 total 是 5
So that's nine plus five equals 14,
所以 9 加 5 等于 14
and our total gets up to 14.
于是 total 变成了 14
So, we reached the end of this loop, go back up,
到达循环尾部 回来
add one more to i,
再给 i 加 1
and then we do this condition again.
再次进行条件判断
Is four less than or equal to three?
4 是否小于或等于 3 呢？
Nope, it's not anymore.
不是的 所以条件不再为真
So we do not step into that loop anymore,
所以我们不再进入循环
and we just skip down here to return total.
直接跳到这下面 返回 total 的值
So, that not value of total at that point is 14,
所以现在 total 的值为 14
which is the output of this function,
也就是这个函数的输出结果
that is if the input is three.
也就是当输入值为 3 时的函数结果
Brilliant. You could also try to trace it
棒极了 你也可以试着跟踪看看
with larger input values and see if it works for that as well.
输入更大的值 观察函数是否同样奏效